Guide to the Henry Charlton Bastian papers, 1841-1932 and undated, bulk 1870-1920
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Correspondence Series, 1856-1932 and undated, bulk 1870-1920, (3 boxes)
  - Kebbel, T. S.: Autograph letter signed to Miss Bastian. 3 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - Mary, Albert and Alexandre: Verification and confirmation of Dr. Charlton H. Bastian's experiments on the origin of life. Manuscript document written after B's death, undated (Box 3)
  - Orécul(?), A.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian (?) concerning abiogenesis research. 4 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - Osler, Grace: Autograph letter signed to Sybil Bastian. 2pp, undated but post 1919 (Box 3)
  - Parkinson, J.: Autograph letter of condolence signed to Mrs. Bastian. 2 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - Perrin, Hester: Autograph letter signed to Bastian concerning the death of Sir John Banks. 4 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - Ritchie, Anne: Autograph letter signed to Lady Albert. 2 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - Robertson, [---]: Autograph postcard signed to Mrs. Bastian. 1 page, undated (Box 3)
  - Saleeby, Caleb Williams: Typed letter signed to Bastian asking him to contribute to Methuen's new Scientific Series. 2 pp., undated but probably 1905 (Box 3)
  - Wright, Jonathan: Autograph note signed to Bastian, plus enclosed clipping on Mutations of Plants. 1 page, undated (Box 3)
  - [---]: Autograph letter signed to Sybil. 4 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - [---]: Autograph letter signed to Onslow. 2 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - [---]: Autograph letter signed to Sybil. 1 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - [---]: Autograph letter signed to Sybil. 2 pp., undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes and autographs, undated (Box 3)
- Personal Papers Series, 1882-1919 and undated, (1 box, 2 oversize folders)
  Includes materials such as a newsprint detailing London's Victory March in 1919, various Christmas cards, obituaries, and Bastian's funeral oration. Arranged chronologically, with undated items at the end.
  - Map of Chambery (France), 1882 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Taubman, F. M.: Hand-drawn Christmas card to Dr.and Mrs. Bastian. 1 page, 1903 (Box 3)
  - Wilberforce, Basil: Life in Him. Funeral oration for Bastian. 4 proof sheets plus autograph note to Mrs. Bastian, 1915 (Box 3)
  - Route of to-day's great victory march. Clipping from the London Times, July 19, 1919 (Opaperfolder 2)
  - Obituary of Mrs. Bastian. Clippng from unidentified newspaper, undated (Box 3)
  - Thayer Smith, W.: Pencil sketch of Toynbee (brother of Arnold Toynbee) by W. Thayer Smith, undated (Box 3)
  - Cabinet photograph of Strachan-Davidson (classical scholar, Master of Balliol College at Oxford) with manuscript verse on verso, undated (Box 3)
  - Clipping from unidentified newspaper concerning Kew Gardens, with note in Bastian's hand, undated (Box 3)
  - Cabinet photograph of William Pennington Cocks (British naturalist) by Alfred Ellis, together with card with Cocks’ birthdate, pen sketch (by Cocks?) of a skeleton sitting on a globe, and a Welsh motto, undated (before 1878) (Box 3)
  - Cabinet photograph of Scottish literary critic, historian and editor David Masson by Elliot and Fry, with Masson's autograph signature on recto and inscription to Mrs. Bastian on verso, undated (Box 3)
  - Cabinet photograph of Arthur M. Edwards by Huff, with Edward's autograph inscription and signature on the verso, undated. (Box 3)
    Edwards was an American physician; married to Emma Ward Edwards, one of the first female doctors in New Jersey.
  - Casting Pearls: Satire printed in Punch, undated (Box 3)
  - Souvenir engravings of Elizabeth Castle and Gate House, Kenilworth, undated (Box 3)
  - Caricature of Prof. Augustus de Morgan by unidentified artist, undated (Box 3)
- Professional Papers Series, 1841-1919 and undated, (1 box)
  Materials relating to Bastian's professional development and research, including reprints of Bastian's work, research notes, scientific photographs, several diplomas, and reviews of publications and research. Subjects concern aphasia, paralyis, abiogenesis, and kinesthesia, among others. Arranged mostly chronologically, with undated items at the end.
  - Rumball, James Quilter: Phrenological development. Printed form with manuscript evaluation of Bastian by Rumball. 2ff., 1841 (Box 3)
  - Apothecaries’ Hall: Printed preliminary examination dated Mar. 18. 1 page., 1856 (Box 3)
  - Apothecaries’ Hall: Printed notice certifying that Bastian had passed the Hall's examination. 1 page, 1856 (Box 3)
  - University of London: Bastian's Bachelor of Medicine diploma. 1 sheet, printed on parchment, 1863 (Box 3)
  - Bastian: Portfolio of 22 ink and pencil drawings of filaria and other scientific organisms, 1861-1862 (Box 4)
  - Photographs of cerebellum. Eleven photographs (some trimmed), in envelope addressed to Bastian, 1868 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Sensation and perception—I. In Nature, no. 8: 213-214. Whole number. Pencil correction by Bastian, 1869 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Sensation and perception—II. In Nature, no. 12: 309-311. Whole number, 1870 (Box 4)
  - Royal College of Physicians: Printed notice naming Bastian a Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians. 2 pp., 1870 (Box 4)
  - Sanderson, J. Burdon: Preparations showing the results of certain experimental inquiries relating to the nature of the infective agent in pyaemia, 6 pp., 1872. With Bastian's marginal notes. (Box 4)
  - Sanderson, J. Burdon: Criticisms of Dr. Chauveau of Lyons on the discussion of the Pathological Society on pyaemia, cutting from British Medical Journal. Bastian's pencil notes in margin, 1872-1873 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The evolution hypothesis, and the origin of life. Part II. Extract from Contemporary Review. 703-720 pp., 1874 (Box 4)
  - Review of Bastian's On Paralysis from Brain Disease in its Common Forms. Extract from Birmingham Medical Review. 217-222 pp. Docketed by Bastian, 1875 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The brain as an organ of mind. Autograph manuscript outline. 4 pp., 1875 (Box 4)
  - Review of Bastian's On Paralysis from Brain Disease in its Common Forms. Extract from Glasgow Medical Journal. 523-528 pp. Docketed by Bastian, 1875 (Box 4)
  - New York World review of Bastian's On Paralysis from Brain Disease in its Common Forms. Cutting, 1875 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Paralysis from brain disease. Additions and alterations. Autograph manuscript. 2 pp., 1876 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Chap. XIII. On the scope of mind or mental phenomena. Autograph manuscript. 5 pp., 1877 (Box 4)
  - Tyndall, John: Spontaneous generation. Extract from The Nineteenth Century. Annotated in pencil by Bastian, 1877 (Box 4)
  - Medical Society, University College, London: List of members, Oct. 1, 1879. Broadsheet, 1879 (Box 4)
  - Macmillan and Co.: Statement sheet for Bastian's Lowest Organisms. Printed sheet completed in manuscript, 1880 (Box 4)
  - Review of The Brain as an Organ of Mind. Cutting from the Pall Mall Gazette, 1880 (Box 4)
  - Review of The Brain as an Organ of Mind. Cutting from the St. James Gazette, 1880 (Box 4)
  - Notice of The Brain as an Organ of Mind. Cutting from Leeds Mercury. With cover, 1880 (Box 4)
  - Review of The Brain as an Organ of Mind. Extract from Liverpool Albion Press cutting, 1880 (Box 4)
  - Review of The Brain as an Organ of Mind. Extract from Daily Telegraph. Press cutting, 1880 (Box 4)
  - Chamberland, Ch.: Thèses... Recherches sur l’origine et le développement des organismes microscopiques. Inscribed to Bastian, 1879 (Box 4)
  - The Saturday Review: Authors and Publishers, Oct. 1882 (Box 4)
  - Reale Accademia di Medicina di Torino: Diploma issued to Bastian, 1883 (Box 4)
  - Boston Gynecological Society (Societas Gynecologica Bostoniensis): Diploma issued to Bastian, 1885 (Box 4)
  - Review of Bastian's Paralyses, Cerebral, Bulbar and Spinal. Extract from the Lancet, 1886 (Box 4)
  - Royal University of Ireland: Diploma issued to Bastian, 1887 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Prospectus for Paralyses Cerebral, Bulbar and Spinal. 1 sheet. Annotated by Bastian, 1887 (Box 4)
  - Our portrait gallery: Henry Charlton Bastian. Extract from The Provincial Medical Journal, plus portrait, 1887 (Box 4)
  - Eminent medical men [profile of Bastian]. In The Family Doctor and People's Medical Advisor. Whole number, 1887 (Box 4)
  - Review of Bastian's Paralyses, Cerebral, Bulbar and Spinal. Cutting from British Medical Journal, 1887 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph document containing excerpt from a review in the Bristol Medical and Chirurgical Journal. 1 sheet, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Review of Various Forms of Hysterical or Functional Paralysis. Excerpt from The Medical Times and Hospital Gazette. 1 sheet, inscribed, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph notes. 1 sheet, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Review of Various Forms of Hysterical or Functional Paralysis. Cutting from Revue medicale de la Suisse Romande, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Review of Hysterical or Functional Paralysis. Extract from the Medical Press, 1894 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The Beginnings of Life. Autograph document showing costs, receipts, etc., 1896 (Box 4)
  - Review of Various Forms of Hysterical or Functional Paralysis. Cutting from Montreal Medical Journal, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Review of Various Forms of Hysterical or Functional Paralysis. Extract from Birmingham Medical Review, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Review of Various Forms of Hysterical or Functional Paralysis. Extract from British Medical Journal, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph document containing excerpt from a favorable review. 1 sheet, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Mr. Bastian and prepayment meters. Offprint from The Lightning. 1 page. Describes invention by Bastian's son, Charles Orme Bastian, 1897 (Box 4)
  - Review of Aphasia and Other Speech Defects. Cutting from the New York Medical Journal, 1898 (Box 4)
  - Review of Aphasia and Other Speech Defects. Press cutting from unidentified newspaper, 1898 (Box 4)
  - Review of Aphasia and Other Speech Defects. Press cutting from unidentified newspaper, 1898 (Box 4)
  - Errera, Leo: Essais de philosophie botanique. Offprint from Revue de l’Universite de Bruxelles, 1900. Discusses spontaneous generation. (Box 4)
  - Williams & Norgate: Letter regarding pricing of Bastian's Heterogenesis. 1 sheet, 1901 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Notes sur la transformation dans le courant de trois ou quatre jours du contenu entier de l’oeuf de Hydratina Senta… Typed document with autograph annotations. 9 pp., 1901 (Box 4)
  - Bastian; Linnean Society: Correspondence concerning the Society's rejection of Bastian's paper on the resting spores of Vaucheria. 4 pieces, 1901-3 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Second note on the transformation of the entire contents of the egg of Hydratina Senta into a large ciliate belonging to the genus Otostoma. Autograph manuscript. 2ff., 1902 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The evidence for heterogenesis. Offprint from The Medical Press and Circular. 4 pp., 2 copies, 1902 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Works up to 1903. Autograph document showing profits from 8 titles, 1903 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: On some points in connexion with the ordinary development of Vaucheria resting-spores. Offprint from Annals and Magazine of Natural History, 1903 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: On the relations between certain diatoms and the fission-products of a parasitic alga (Chlorochytrium). Offprint from Annals and Magazine of Natural History, 1903 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The appearance of bacteria in normal organs and the significance thereof. Offprint from Lancet. 4 pp., unbound, 1904 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: On the origin of flagellate monads and of fungus-germs from minute masses of zoogloea. Clippings from Nature, 1904 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The simplest kind of protoplasm. Offprint from Knowledge and Scientific News. Pencil correction in Bastian's hand, 1905 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: On the occurrence of certain ciliated infusoria within the eggs of a rotifer, considered from the point of view of heterogenesis. Offprint from Proceedings of the Royal Society, 1905 (Box 4)
  - T. Fisher Unwin: Royalty agreement. Printed document completed in manuscript; signed and docketed by Bastian. 4 pp. Concerning Bastian's Nature and Origin of Living Matter, 1905 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: On the heterogenetic origin of certain ciliated infusoria from the eggs of a rotifer. Autograph manuscript (includes printed matter with Bastian's revisions). 24ff., 1905 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: On some heterogenetic processes. Typescript with Bastian's manuscript additions of a lecture given on Mar. 15, 1906. 8 pp. 2 sheets with signatures of lecture attendees attached, 1906 (Box 4)
  - Review of Bastian's The Evolution of Life. Extract from Times Literary Supplement, 1907 (Box 4)
  - Methuen & Co.: Statement of account for The Evolution of Life. 1 sheet, 1907 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Sull’origine ex novo di bacterii, bacilli, vibrioni, micrococchi, torule e muffe [molds] in certe soluzioni saline… Offprint from Reale Accademia dei Lincei, 1907 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The functions of the kinaesthetic area of the brain. Offprint from Brain: A Journal of Neurology, 1910 (Box 4)
  - A startling scientific discovery. Cutting from Putnam's advance list advertising Bastian's Origin of Life, 1911 (Box 4)
  - Marmol, F. T. del: A problem of latter-day mineralogy: To what extent are minerals sensitive? Extract from The Academy. Mentions Bastian's work, 1913 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph notes, beginning What are the primordial living units? 1 sheet, 1914 (Box 4)
  - Who's Who in Science: clipping of Bastian's biography, 1914 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Experimental data in evidence of the present-day occurrence of spontaneous generation. Offprint from Nature, 1914 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The production at will of either fungus-germs, flagellate monads or amoebae from the ultimate segments of small masses of zoogloea. Offprint from Nature, 1914 (Box 4)
  - Receipt made out to Bastian for one pound and one shilling, 1914 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The forms of lower organisms as dependent upon molecular constitution and environmental conditions. Offprint from Lancet. 3 copies, 1915 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The importance of tyrosine as an aid in the demonstration of the present-day de novo origin of living organisms. Autograph manuscript. 6ff., 1915 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Photos for blocks needed—if any. New edition of Nature and Origin of Living Matter. Set of 17 photomicrographs with autograph manuscript annotations, plus 2 sheets of Bastian's pencil notes, in envelope, 1910 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: La generación espontanea su realidad y lo que ella implica. Offprint from La Semana Medica. Two copies, 1915 (Box 4)
  - Pratelle, Aristide: Ma visite au Fairfield studio. In La Libre Pensée Internationale. Whole issue, 1916 (Box 4)
  - Clipping from Nature concerning Bastian's work, 1917 (Box 4)
  - Copies of letters published in The Lancet on the origin of life: The work of the late Charlton Bastian. Carbon typescript. 27ff., 1919 (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Attention and Volition. Autograph list of recipients of copies. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Copies of Paralyses. Autograph list of recipients of copies. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Hysterical or Functional Paralysis. Autograph list of personal and journal recipients of copies. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph document containing excerpts from favorable reviews of one of Bastian's neurological publications. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Questions re a case of agraphia. Autograph manuscript. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Aud. centre...Visual centre... Autograph document. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Organ of Mind. Autograph list of recipients of copies. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph list of names. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph numbered list of names. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Transv. Lsns of Sp. Cord. Autograph list of recipients. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Papers concerning Sensation and Movement. Autograph list of recipients. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph document containing excerpts from favorable reviews of one of Bastian's neurological works. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian's Paralyses, review clipped from an unidentified newspaper, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph notes written on the back of an envelope, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph document containing excerpts from favorable reviews of one of Bastian's neurological works. 3 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Modes of Origin of Lowest Organisms. Autograph accounting document, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Autograph document containing excerpts from favorable reviews of one of Bastian's neurological works. 1 sheet; envelope addressed to Bastian pasted to the sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Facts and reasonings concerning the heterogenous evolution of living things. Reprinted from Nature, nos. 35, 36, 37. 26 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Relativity of knowledge. Autograph manuscript. 10 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: On the heterogenetic origin of certain ciliated infusoria from the eggs of a rotifer. Autograph manuscript with some printed material amended in manuscript. 3 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Art. on Aphasia sent to above 68 persons... List of names in another hand with annotations by Bastian. 3 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: It has been suggested to me by a distinguished botanist... Autograph manuscript. 3 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Manuscript notes concerning brain weights of eight notable men, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: List of names with numbers and calculations. 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: List of recipients of Organ of Mind. 1 page, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The development of... 1 sheet, undated (Box 4)
  - Favorable reviews of Bastian's work. 1 page, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: Alphabetical letters in another language (Farsi?). 1 page, undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: The latter is a remarkable mould.... 2 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: List of 80 recipients. 2 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Bastian: List of journals on a Williams and Norgate letterhead. 2 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - The British Medical Journal: The Central Nervous Pathways for General Sensibility, undated (Box 4)
  - Caribbeana, undated (Box 4)
  - Fray Mocho en Londres. Newsletter in Spanish concerning the International Congress of Medicine in London; mentions Bastian, 4 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Librairie Germer Bailliere: List of publications. 4 pp., undated (Box 4)
  - Wilberforce, Archdeacon: More than Father.. 1 page, undated (Box 4)
  - Unidentifed author: List of names in French. 1 page, undated (Box 4)
  - Photograph of mushrooms and portion of postcard with biological photograph. Note on verso: By Bastian Wade, Esqr., Blue Town, Sheerners(?), undated (Box 4)
  - Plate V, Finished proof: 7 proofs of micrographs, undated (Box 4)